A Guide to the Floyd Courthouse, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records, 1935-2004
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Floyd Courthouse Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records, 1935-2004
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2005-008
0.5 cu. ft. 1 box
Records of Floyd Courthouse Chapter (Floyd, Virginia) chapter of the National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution, including minutes, yearbooks, and yearly reports.
Daughters of the American Revolution. Floyd Courthouse Chapter. (Floyd, Va)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Floyd Courthouse Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records were donated to the Special Collections in 2005.
Historical Information
Founded in Washington, D. C. in 1890, the National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution arose from a desire on the part of women to participate more fully in an upsurge of patriotism during the late nineteenth century. A volunteer service organization, the DAR's mission objectives involve patriotism, preservation of American history, and education. With membership restricted to women who can prove a direct descent from a participant in the American Revolution, the DAR by 2004 encompassed approximately 170,000 members in nearly 2,300 chapters.
The Floyd Courthouse Chapter of the National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution was organized in Floyd, Virginia on December 23, 1931. Anne Simmons Proffitt served as the first chapter regent. The chapter, with an initial membership of 14, has held regular meetings since its founding, with each meeting featuring a program relating to the DAR's interests in patriotism, historic preservation and education. The chapter has also undertaken various projects to coincide with DAR objectives.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the records of the Floyd Courthouse Chapter of the National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution. The collection consists largely of the chapter's meeting minutes, which also include attendance rolls. The collection also contains several of the chapter's yearbooks. Also found here, under the title "Centennial Gift to the Chapters of the Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution," is a set of the chapter's yearly reports to the state organization for the years 1932 to 1997. Among the miscellaneous materials found in the collection are a few pieces of correspondence, a 1959 speech text, and newspaper clippings.
Arrangement
The collection in arranged in five series by type of content. Series I: Administrative Information includes history of the organization generated by the chapter. Series II: Awards contains a newspaper clipping about the award-giving history. Series III: Correspondence consists of July 1983 letters from the chapter and national organization. Series IV: Minutes contains more than 50 years of chapter meeting minutes. Series V: Publications includes individual newspaper clippings and several editions of chapter yearbooks.
The series are organized in alphabetical order. Materials within each series are in chronological order at the folder level.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Ms 1995-019, Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records, 1890-2010. Finding aid available online.
Ms2014-013, Colonel William Christian Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records, 1935-1990s. Finding aid available online.
Library Catalog by the National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution. CS47 .D38 1983 Special Collections.
Proceedings of the ... State Conference, Virginia Daughters of the National Society Daughters of the American Revolution (journal). 53rd (1949) - 55th (1951) editions. E202.5 .V85 Special Collections.
Virginia State Conference of the National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution (journal). 32nd (1928)-35th (1931) editions. E202.5 .V85 Special Collections.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Daughters of the American Revolution. Floyd Courthouse Chapter. (Floyd, Va)
Geographical Names:
Floyd County (Va.)
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Women--History
Contents List
- Series I: Administrative Information, 1959, 2004, n.d.
  - Address to the Meeting of the VA DAR, March 17, 1959 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Information About the Floyd Courthouse Chapter DAR's Organization and History, c. 2004 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Cover of a Pamphlet for the Floyd Courthouse DAR Chapter (Box-folder 1-22)
- Series II: Awards, 1997
  - "Centennial Gift to the Chapters of the Virginia Daughters of the American Revolution from Mrs. H. T. N. Graves, State Regent," [1997] (Box-folder 1-13)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1983
  - NSDAR Correspondence, July 1983 (Box-folder 1-19)
- Series IV: Minutes, 1935-1985, n.d.
  - 1935-1942 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - 1943-1950 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - 1951-1955 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - 1956-1959 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - 1960-1968 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - 1969-1975 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - 1976-1978 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - 1981-1982 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - 1983-1985 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Undated Minutes (Box-folder 1-18)
- Series V: Publications, 1959-2001, n.d.
  - Yearbooks, 1959-1989 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Yearbooks, 1992-2001 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1986, n.d.
    - "DAR Good Citizen Named" Article, The Floyd Press, January 3, 1986 (Box-folder 1-14)
    - "Floyd Courthouse DAR has Meeting," The Floyd Press, March 20, 1986 (Box-folder 1-21)
    - "DAR Patriots Take Conservative Stand" by Brian O'Neill (Box-folder 1-17)
    - Photocopy of a Newspaper Photograph of the Fall Conference of the Southwest District DAR (Box-folder 1-20)